In this video we talk about
在这段视频中我们将会讨论
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
matrix, matrix multiplication or
矩阵 矩阵的乘法以及
how to multiply two matrices together.
如何将两个矩阵相乘
When we talk about the method
我们会使用这样一种方法
in linear regression for how
在线性回归中用以解决
to solve for the parameters,
参数计算的问题
theta zero and theta one, all in one shot.
这种方法会把θ0、θ1等参数都放在一起来计算
So, without needing an iterative algorithm like gradient descent.
也就是说 我们不需要一个迭代的梯度下降算法
When we talk about that algorithm,
当我们谈到这个算法的时候
it turns out that matrix, matrix
就会发现矩阵以及矩阵间的乘法运算
multiplication is one of the key steps that you need to know.
是你必须理解的关键步骤之一
So, let's, as usual, start with an example.
所以让我们像往常那样 从一个例子开始
Let's say I have two matrices
比方说 我有两个矩阵
and I want to multiply them together.
我想将它们相乘
Let me again just reference this
让我先只是按照这个例子做一遍（乘法）
example and then I'll tell you in a little bit what happens.
然后告诉你这其中运算的细节
So, the first thing
那么  我要做的第一件事是
I'm gonna do is, I'm going
我先把
to pull out the first
右边这个矩阵的第一列
column of this matrix on the right.
提取出来
And I'm going to take this
然后我将会把
matrix on the left and
左边的这个矩阵和
multiply it by, you know, a vector.
之前取出来的这一列（前面提过的，向量）相乘
That's just this first column, OK?
这只是第一列  是吧？
And it turns out if I
然后我们可以看到 如果我
do that I am going to get the vector 11, 9.
这么做 我就会得到向量（11,9）
So, this is the same matrix
所以这是与上个视频的矩阵
vector multiplication as you saw in the last videos.
和向量的乘法是一样的
I worked this out in advance so, I know it's 11, 9.
我已经提前算出了这个结果 是（11,9）
And, then, the second thing
那么 之后的第二件事
I'm going to do is, I'm going
我要做的就是
to pull out the second column,
我将把第二列再单独提出出来
this matrix on the right and
右边这个矩阵的第二列
I am then going to
然后我将要把它和
take this matrix on the left,
左边这个矩阵相乘
right, so, it will be that matrix,
是的吧  所以 这就是那个矩阵
and multiply it by
用右边的第二列
that second column on the right.
来乘以这个矩阵
So, again, this is a matrix
因此 同样的 这是一个矩阵和
vector multiplication set, which
向量的乘法运算  这
you saw from the previous video, and
就是你从上一个视频所学到的
it turns out that if you
如果你这么做
multiply this matrix and this
把这个矩阵和这个向量相乘
vector, you get 10,
你会得到
14 and by
（10,14）这个结果
the way, if you want to practice
顺便说一下 如果你想练习
your matrix vector multiplication, feel
矩阵和向量的乘法运算
free to pause the video and check this product yourself.
那么就先暂停下视频  自己算一算结果对不对
Then, I'm just going
好吧 现在我仅仅需要
to take these two results and
将得到的这两个结果放在一起
put them together, and that will be my answer.
那么这就是我的答案了
So, turns out the
那么 我们可以看到
outcome of this product is going
计算结果是
to be a 2 by 2 matrix, and
一个2 x 2的矩阵
The way I am going to fill
我用来填充这个矩阵的方法
in this matrix is just by
就是
taking my elements 11,
把我的（11,9）
9 and plugging them here, and
填在这里
taking 10, 14 and plugging
把（10，14）填在
them into the second column.
第二列
Okay?
是的吧？
So, that was the mechanics of
所以 这就是如何
how to multiply a matrix by
将两个矩阵相乘的
another matrix.
详细方法与过程
You basically look at the
每次你只需要看
second matrix one column at a time, and you assemble the answers.
第二个矩阵的一列    然后把你的答案拼凑起来
And again, we will step
再次强调下 我们将一步步的来计算
through this much more carefully in
几秒中的时间里需要非常仔细
a second, but I just
但我也要指出
want to point out also, this
我也要指出的是
first example is a 2x3 matrix matrix.
第一个例子是一个2X3矩阵
Multiplying that by a
乘以一个
3x2 matrix, and the
3x2的矩阵 他们相乘
outcome of this product, it
得到的结果
turns out to be a 2x2
是一个2x2的
matrix.
矩阵
And again, we'll see in a second why this was the case.
我们将很快知道为什么是这个结果
All right.
好的
That was the mechanics of the calculation.
这是计算的技巧
Let's actually look at the
让我们再看看
details and look at what
这其中的细节
exactly happened.
看看究竟发生了什么
Here are details.
下面就是详细的过程
I have a matrix A and
我有一个矩阵A
I want to multiply that
我要把它乘以
with a matrix B, and the result
矩阵B  其结果
will be some new matrix C. And
会是一个新的矩阵C
it turns out you can only
并且你会发现你只能
multiply together matrices whose
相乘那些维度
dimensions match so A
匹配的矩阵
is an m by n matrix,
因此如果A是一个m×n的矩阵
so m columns, n columns and
就是说m行n列
I am going to multiply
我将要用它与
that with an n by o
一个n×o的矩阵相乘
and it turns out this n
并且实际上这里的n
here must match this n
必须匹配这里的这个n
here, so the number of columns
所以第一个矩阵的列的数目
in first matrix must equal to the number of rows in second matrix.
必须等于第二矩阵中的行的数目
And the result of this
并且相乘得到的结果
product will be an M
结果会是一个m×o的矩阵
by O matrix, like the the matrix C here.
就像这个矩阵C这样
And, in the previous
并且 在前面的视频中
video, everything we did corresponded
我们所做的一切都符合这个规则
to this special case of OB
这是一种当矩阵B的o值
equal to 1.
等于1的特殊情况（指的是矩阵和向量相乘）
Okay?
明白了吗？
That was, that was in case of B being a vector.
这是在B是一个向量的情况下
But now, we are going to
但是现在 我们要处理
view of the case of values of O larger than 1.
O的值大于1的情况
So, here's how you
所以 这里就是你怎样
multiply together the two matrices.
把两个矩阵相乘
In order to get, what
为了得到结果
I am going to do is
我要做的就是
I am going to take the
我将要取
first column of B
B矩阵的第一列
and treat that as a vector,
把取出的这列看成一个向量
and multiply the matrix A,
并乘以矩阵A
with the first column of B,
用B矩阵的第一列
and the result of that will
这个计算结果将是
be a M by 1 vector,
m×1的矩阵（也就是一个向量）
and we're going to put that over here.
我们把结果先放在这里
Then, I'm going to
然后 我将要取
take the second column
B矩阵的
of B, right, so,
第二列
this is another n by
那么我会又得到一个n×1的向量
one vector, so, this column
也就是 这里的这一列
here, this is right, n
这是正确的
by one, those are n dimensional
n×1的矩阵 也就是n维的向量
vector, gonna multiply this
我将要把这个矩阵
matrix with this n by one vector.
和这些n乘1的向量相乘
The result will be
其结果将是
a M dimensional vector,
一个m维的向量
which we'll put there.
然后我会把结果先放在那里
And, so on.
依此类推
Okay?
对吧？
And, so, you know, and then
那么 你知道的
I'm going to take the third
我开始取第三列
column, multiply it by
把它和这个矩阵相乘
this matrix, I get a M dimensional vector.
我又得到了一个M维向量
And so on, until you get
依此类推 直到你计算到了
to the last column times,
最后一列
the matrix times the
矩阵乘以
lost column gives you
你取到的最后一列
the lost column of C.
就是C的最后一列
Just to say that again.
再说一遍
The ith column of the
矩阵C的第i列
matrix C is attained
是根据把
by taking the matrix A and
矩阵A与
multiplying the matrix A with
矩阵B的第i列
the ith column of the
相乘得到的
matrix B for the values
结果
of I equals 1, 2
依次相加
up through O. Okay ?
从1,2到o依次相加的 对吧？
So, this is just a summary
那么 我们在这里做一个总结
of what we did up there
我们总结了我们为了
in order to compute the matrix
计算矩阵C所做的步骤
C.  Let's look at just one more example.
让我们再看一个例子
Let 's say, I want to multiply together these two matrices.
比方说我想把这两个矩阵相乘
So, what I'm going to
那么我首先要做的是
do is, first pull
先取出
out the first column
我的第二个矩阵的
of my second matrix, that
第一列
was matrix B, that was
就是这个矩阵B 这就是
my matrix B on the previous slide.
上一张幻灯片上出现的矩阵B
And, I therefore, have this
因此 我就这么
matrix times my vector and
用矩阵和我取的向量相乘
so, oh, let's do this calculation quickly.
所以    让我们快速的计算这个结果
There's going to be equal to,
这等于
right, 1, 3 times 0,
没错  （1,3）乘以（0,3）
3 so that gives 1
所以 就是
times 0, plus 3 times 3.
1x0+3x3（9）
And, the second element
此外 第二元素
is going to be 2,
就是（2，5）
5 times 0, 3 so, that's going to
乘以（0，3）
be two times 0 plus 5
就是0x2+5x3（15）
times 3 and that is
那么结果出来了
9,15, actually didn't
（9,15）实际上该用绿色的颜色标记
write that in green, so this
所以这就是（9.15）
is nine fifteen, and then mix.
那么
I am going to pull out
我将同样的取出
the second column of this,
这个的第二列
and do the corresponding
做相同的计算
calculation so there's this
所以
matrix times this vector 1, 2.
这是这个矩阵乘以（1,2）
Let's also do this
让我们快点算吧
quickly, so that's one times
所以这是
one plus three times two.
1x1 + 3x2
So that deals with that
那么这就处理了这一行
row, let's do the
让我们计算另一行
other one, so let's see,
让我们来看看
that gives me two times
这次是
one plus times two,
2x1 + 5x2
so that is going to
因此这就等于
be equal to, let's see,
我们看一下
one times one plus three times
1x1 + 3x1结果是4
one is four and two
2x1 + 5x2
times one plus five times two
结果是
is twelve.
So now I have these two
所以现在我有两个这个了
you, and so my
因此我得到的
outcome, so the product
这两个矩阵
of these two matrices is going
相乘的结果就是
to be, this goes
这个在这儿
here and this
那个放那边
goes here, so I
所以我得到了
get nine fifteen and
9,15和
four twelve and you
4,12
may notice also that the result
你也可能会注意到这个结果
of multiplying a 2x2 matrix
一个2×2的矩阵
with another 2x2 matrix.
乘以另一个2x2的矩阵
The resulting dimension is going
这个维度会是
to be that first two times
第一个矩阵的2乘以第二的矩阵的2
that second two, so the result
所以这个结果本身
is itself also a two by two matrix.
也是一个2x2的矩阵
Finally let me show you
最后让我告诉你
one more neat trick you can
一个更加具体的技巧    你可以
do with matrix matrix multiplication.
在矩阵和矩阵的乘法中使用
Let's say as before that we
比方说 在这之前 我们
have four houses whose
有四间房子
prices we want to predict,
我们要预测其价格
only now we have three
但是现在我们有三个
competing hypothesis shown here
不同的竞争假设集在这儿
on the right, so if
在右侧 因此 如果
you want to So apply all
你想要去把
3 competing hypotheses to
这三个竞争假设集用来
all four of the houses, it
适应这4个房屋的数据
turns out you can do that
那么你可以这样做
very efficiently using a
这将非常高效
matrix matrix multiplication so here
我们使用这里的矩阵乘法来计算
on the left is my usual
左边是我通常使用的矩阵
matrix, same as from the
这与我上个视频
last video where these values
一样  这些值就是
are my housing prices and I put ones there on the left as well.
我的住房价格   我把这些值也放在左边
And, what I'm going to
那么 我要去做的就是
do is construct another matrix, where
构造另一个矩阵
here these, the first
这个矩阵的第一列
column, is this minus
是-40
40 and two five and
0.25
the second column is this two
第二列是
hundred open one and so
（200.0.1）
on and it
以此类推
turns out that if you
事实证明  如果你
multiply these two matrices
把这两个矩阵相乘
what you find is that, this
你就会发现得到了结果的
first column, you know,
第一列  你知道的
oh, well how do you get this first column, right?
那么你怎么得到这个第一列呢？
A procedure from matrix
这就要用到我们讲过的
matrix multiplication is the way
矩阵和矩阵相乘的过程
you get this first column, is
你得到的这个矩阵的第一列
you take this matrix and you
通过你用这个矩阵
multiply it by this
乘以
first column, and we
这个矩阵的第一列
saw in the previous video that this
这是我们从之前的视频中看到过的
is exactly the predicted
这就是从第一个假设
housing prices of the
预测出的
first hypothesis, right?
住房价格 对吗？
Of this first hypothesis here.
就是这里的这个假设集
And, how about a second column?
那么 第二列是什么呢？
Well, how do setup the second column?
那么 我们应该怎么计算第二列呢？
The way you get the second column
用来得到第二列的方法
is, well, you take this
就是
matrix and you multiply by this second column.
用这个矩阵乘以这个矩阵的第二列
And so this second column turns
那么得到的第二列就是
out to be the predictions of
基于第二个假设
the second hypothesis of
做出的预测结果
the second hypothesis up there,
第二个假设集是在那里
and similarly for the third column.
对于第三列 我们也能得到类似的结果
And so, I didn't step
那么 我并没有
through all the details but hopefully
把详细的细节列出
you just, feel free to
不过 我还是希望你们能够把
pause the video and check
视频暂停下 自己算一算
the math yourself and check
检查下结果对不对
that what I just claimed really is true.
检验下我刚才计算的结果的正确性
But it turns out that by
那么 实际上通过
constructing these two matrices, what
构建这两个矩阵
you can therefore do is very
你就可以
quickly apply all three
快速的把这三个假设集
hypotheses to all four
应用到所有四个
house sizes to get,
房子的尺寸中来计算价格了
you know, all twelve predicted
你看 所有的12种预测到的价格是
prices output by your
通过你的假设集
three hypotheses on your four houses.
以及你的四个房屋数据集得到的
So one matrix multiplications
所以 一次矩阵乘法操作
that you manage to make 12
就使你做出了12种预测
predictions and, even
更好的是
better, it turns out that
事实证明
in order to do that matrix
为了做到
multiplication and there are
矩阵间的乘法
lots of good linear algebra libraries
有很多很好的线性代数库函数
in order to do this
都是为了做到这一点
multiplication step for you,
为你实现矩阵乘法
and no matter so pretty
而且不管你用的是
much any reasonable programming language that you might be using.
多么合理的编程语言
Certainly all the top ten
当然 当下最流行的
most popular programming languages will have great linear algebra libraries.
编程语言中的前十名都有很棒的线性代数函数库
And they'll be good thing are
这是很好的事情
highly optimized in order
我们能够在高度优化下
to do that, matrix matrix
做到矩阵
multiplication very efficiently, including
和矩阵间高效的乘法 包括
taking, taking advantage of
采取了一些优化处理的方式
any parallel computation that
如并行计算
your computer may be capable
如果你的电脑支持的话
of, when your computer has multiple
当你的计算机有多个
calls or lots of
调度或者
multiple processors, within a processor sometimes
多个处理器  一个处理器内有时
there's there's parallelism as well called symdiparallelism [sp].
存在并行的计算 我们称之为SIMD Parallelism
The computer take care of
在计算机管理机制下
and you should, there are
你应该有
very good free libraries
非常不错的免费类库
that you can use to do
你可以用来做
this matrix matrix multiplication very
高效的矩阵间的乘法计算
efficiently so that you
因此你就能
can very efficiently, you
你知道的
know, makes lots of predictions of lots of hypotheses.
方便地计算有很多假设集时的预测数据